Guide to the Jacques Barzun's Collection of Hector Berlioz Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Subseries I.2: Originals relating to Berlioz
    - Sembat, Marcel To: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Dec. 09, 1910, (2p. t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Smithson, Hariet C. To: Le Ministre de l'Interieur, Paris, Aug. 15, 1830, (3p. a.l.s. (photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Societe des "Amis de Balzac" To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, Nov. 29, 1911, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Societe Internationale de Musique, Section de Paris To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], [Paris], [22 Apr. 1914]; 27 May 1914, (2 t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Spencer-Brunton, Enid To: Tom S. Wotton, [London], Dec 3, 1897; May 2, 1898, (2 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 82 - 83)
    - Spontini, Gasparo To: Royal College of Music, Paris, Aug. 12, 1843, (1p. a.l.s. (photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Starkie, Enid Mary To: Jacques Barzun, Oxford, Mar. 18, 1958; May 3, 1958, (1p. t.l.s with copies of 2 related letters from J. Barzun, 1p. t.l.s. with copy of reply, ) (Box 2, Folder 85 - 86)
    - Strauss, Richard To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Garmisch; Franfurt am Main, Dec. 23, 1908; Dec. 16, 1910, (1p. a.l.s., 1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 87 - 88)
    - Terry, Julia Nielson (Mrs. Fred) To: T.S. Wotton, Ridgemount Gardens, Jun. 24, 1894, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Theatre Lyrique Municipal de la Gaite To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, Dec. 06, 1910, (1p. a.l.s. (signed by Administrateur General), ) (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Thompson, Herbert To: W.S. Wotton, Leeds, Feb. 15, 1935; Oct. 24, 1935, (2 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 91 - 92)
    - Tiersot, Julien To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, Dec. 1, 1908 - Dec. 14 1912, (2 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Trianon Lyrique To: Henri-Martin Berlioz, Paris, Oct. 29, 1912, (1p. a.l.s. (signed by the sec'y of the Director), ) (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Trilling, Lionel To: Jaques Barzun, New York, Nov. 1, 1947; [Jul. 1959], (1 a.p.c.s., 1p. (incomplete) t.l. ) (Box 2, Folder 95 - 96)
    - Turner, Walter James Redfern To: Jacques Barzun, [London], Feb. 03, 1935, (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Vanburgh, Irene To: Tom S. Wotton, [London], n.d., (1p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Van Dieren, Bernard To: T.S. Wotton, London, Sep. - Oct. 1935, (3 t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Vaux, Maurice To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Saillans; Paris, 1909-1911, (4 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 100 - 101)
    - Verdi, Guiseppi To: [Hector Berlioz], Milan, Jan. 12, 1847, (3p. a.l.s. (photostat with t.s. translation), ) (Box 2, Folder 102)
      [original in British Museum]
    - Vernaeldon, Albert to: Henri-Martin Barzun, Paris, Dec. 16, 1909; Dec. 9, 1910, (2 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Viardot, Pauline To: Hector Berlioz, n.p., n.d., (1 a.n.s on ms. of music, ) (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Viaud, Emile To: M. Le Secretaire General de la Foundation Berlioz, Paris, May. 13, 1911, (1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Villiard To: [Henri-Martin Barzun], Paris, Sep. 21, 1908; Dec. 8, 1911, (2p. a.l.s., 2p. a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Wagner, Richard To: [Theodore Winkler], Meudon, Oct. 24 ,1841, (2p. a.l.s. with t.s. translation, ) (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Wagner, Richard To: Hector Berlioz, [Paris], Jan. 21, 1860, (1p. a.l.s. (photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 108)
      [Original in Bibliotheque de Grenoble]
    - Warlock, Peter To: Tom S. Wotton, London, Nov. 1929 - Jan. 1930, (3 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Watelet, E. To: Paris, Sep. 10, 1909, (1p. a.d.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Weeks, Edward To: Jacques Barzun, Boston, Jan. 16, 1950, (1p. t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Weingartner, Felix To: Foundation Hector Berlioz, Vienna, Dec. 19, 1908; Dec. 19, 1910, (2 t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 112 - 113)
    - White, WIlliam Anthony Parker To: Jacques Barzun, Berkeley, CA., Jun. 28, 1961; Jul. 10, 1961, (1 t.l.s. (with copy of reply), 1 t.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 114 - 115)
    - Wood, Henry J. To: Tom S. Wotton, London; Brighton Herts; on board the Aquitania, 1909-1933, (6 t.l.s. 3 a.l.s., ) (Box 2, Folder 116 - 120)
  - Subseries I.3: Copies
    Photostats and/or typescripts of autographed correspondence by Berlioz from various repositories - a part of the research materials assembled by Barzun. Arranged alphabetically by recepient.
    - Berlioz, Hector to: n.p., n.d., (3 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 121 - 123)
      [Originals in: Harvard University Library; Sibley Musical Library, U. of Rochester]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Paris, n.d., (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 124)
      [Original in Sibley Musical Library, U. of Rochester. Signed by Berlioz and others.]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: "Madame", [Paris], Jan. 17, n.y., (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 2, Folder 125)
      [Originals in Cortot Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: "Cher Maitre", n.p., May 19, 1842, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: "Messieurs", Berlin, Apr. 24, 1843, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: "Monsieur le Prefet", [Paris], [Aug. 1845], (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Paris, Feb. 18, 1851, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 129)
      [Original in British Museum]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: London, Jul. 2, [1851], (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 2, Folder 130)
      [Original in Theatre de la Monnaie, Brussels]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: n.p., Jul. 12, 1856, (2p. a.l.s. (Photocopy), ) (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Paris], Nov. 24, 1857, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Paris], Feb. 12, 1859, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 2, Folder 133)
      [Original in NYPL]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Paris], May 10, 1860, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Paris], [Oct. 1863], (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 135)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Paris, Oct. 10, 1865, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 2, Folder 136)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Paris], Feb. 25, 1868, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 2, Folder 137)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Alexandre, Edouard, [Paris], Apr. 6, 1853, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      [Original in LOC]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ambros, Auguste Wilhelm, [Paris], Feb. 15, 1846, (2p. a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Amussat, Jean Zulema, [Paris], n.d., (5 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 3 - 7)
      [Originals in Stanford University Libraries]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Balzac, Honore de, [Paris], n.d., (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 8)
      [Original in Institue Suel de France]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Baudillon, M., n.p., n.d., (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 9)
      [Original in Stanford University Libraries]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bennaci, M., Paris, Sep. 24, 1843, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 10)
      [Original in Cortot Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bennet, Toussaint, [Paris], 1855 - 1860, (3 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 11 - 13)
      [Original in Wannemacher Collection, Philadelphia]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bennet, Toussaint and Theodore Ritter, [Paris], 1856, (4p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bennet, Madame Toussaint, [Paris], Jul. 1, 1856, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Berlioz, Louis], [Paris], Jul. 8, 1863, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Berlioz, Louis Joseph, London, Nov. 7, 1847, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bertin, Armand, [Paris], Feb. 12, 1840, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bitterman, Ritter, Turin, Apr. 12-14, 1856, (2 a.l.s. (photocopy), ) (Box 3, Folder 19 - 20)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bizet, Georges, n.p., n.d., (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 21)
      [From the Mina Curtiss Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Boisselot], M., [Paris], Jul. 1852, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Berlioz, Hector Association des Artistes Musiciens. to: Boule, Madame Theodore, Paris, Nov. 26, 1857, (1p. l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 23)
      [Original in Bibliotheque de Grenoble. Signed by Berlioz and other committee members]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Brandus, L.], [Paris], Mar. 1852, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 24)
      [Original in Sibley Musical Library, U. of Rochester]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Broadwood, [Henry Fowler], Paris, Apr. 6, 1862, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Broderotti], M., Paris, Jun. 28, 1863, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Busset, M., Ingenieur a Dijon, [Paris], Oct. 1836, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Carvalho, Leon, [Paris], Jul. 15, [1863], (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Catelin, [Adolphe], n.p., n.d., (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Chelard, Hippolyte, Leipzig, Feb. 2, [1848], (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 30)
      [Original in collection of Martin Bernstein]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Chorley, Henry Fothergill, Dresden, Paris, 1854, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 31 - 32)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Choudens, Antoine, [Paris], Jan. 19, 1864, (2 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 33 - 34)
      [Originals in Bibliotheque du Conservatoire and Alfred C. Jerome Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Clarke, Mary Cowden, Paris, Oct. 2, 1855, (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Cornelius, Peter, Leipzig, Dec. 6, 1953, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Bertold Damcke, Petersbourg, Nov. 26/14, 1867, (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 37)
      [Original in Clark Memorial Library, UCLA]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: David, Ferdinand, Dresden, Feb. 10, 1843, Apr. 11, 1854, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 38 - 39)
      [Original in Rosenthal Collection, Oxford]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: David, [Paris], Jan. 7, 1854, (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Delaporte, M., [Paris], [Mar. 7, n.y.], (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 41)
      [Original in Carl Tollefson Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Delsarte, [Gustave], Paris, Apr. 30, 1857, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Demeur, J. A., [Paris], [1855], (2 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 43 - 44)
      [Original in Collection of Dr. V. Gurewich]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Desmarets], M., Brunswick, Mar. 6, 1843, (4p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Dietsch, Pierre Louis, [Paris], n.d., (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Dingelstedt, Franz, Frankfort, Aug. 16, 1853, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 47)
      [Original in Boston Public Library]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Dobre, Mademoiselle, n.p., n.d., (Ms. d. s. (photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 48)
      [Original in LOC. Signed by Berlioz and others]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Donadieu, M., [Paris], Feb. 1, 1848, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Donizetti, Gaetano, [Paris], [1843], (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 50)
      [Original in Harvard University Library]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Dortfeld, M., Paris, Oct. 2, 1867, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 51)
      [Original in Collection of Edwin Franko Goldman]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Duboeuf, Estelle, [Paris], Dec. 19, [1864], (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Duboys, Albert, Paris, Rome, Grenoble, 1825 - 1866, (8 a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 53 - 60)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Duchene, L., [Paris], n.d., (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 61)
      [Original in Bibliotheque de Grenoble.]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Duveyier, Charles, Rome, Jul. 28, 1831, (3p. a.l. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ella, John, Paris, Apr. 6, 1956; May 27, 1863, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 63 - 64)
      [Originals in Sibley Musical Library, U. of Rochester]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Erkel, Franz, Paris, Jan. 25, 1860, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Escudier, [Leon], Baden Baden, Aug. 2, 1862, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: de Ferrieres, Theophile, Paris, [184?], (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Fetis, M., Paris, Oct. 20, 1866, (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Fiorentino, Pier Angelo, [Paris], [Apr. 1855], (2p. a.l.s. (Typescript and ms copy), ) (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Flobert, Gustave, Paris, Nov. 4, 1862, (2p. a.l.s. (Typescript and ms. copy), ) (Box 3, Folder 70)
      [From: Flaubert, Salambo (ed. Conard), 504]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: France, Queen of, [Paris], Aug. 4, 1840; Mar. 12, 1845, (2 a.l.s. (Typescript and ms. copy), ) (Box 3, Folder 71 - 72)
      [Originals in NYPL and Bibliotheque Nationale]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ganz, Leopold, [Paris], Jun. 24, 1847; Jun. 24, 1848, (2 a.l.s. (Typescript, photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 73 - 74)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gasparini, M., Paris, Dec. 17, 1865, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gatayes, Joseph Leon, Paris, Apr. 1, 1851, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Gautier, Theophile], Paris, [Nov.-Dec. 1835], (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gounod, Charles Francois, Paris, Oct. 11, 1864, (2p. a.l.s. (facsimile and typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Griepenkerl, Robert, London, Breslau, Hanover, Drezden, Gotha, Paris, 1844 - 1856, (8 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 79 - 86)
      [Originals in Bibliotheque de Wolfenbuttel; in Sibley Musical Library, U. of Rochester; Walter O. Shneider Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gruneisen, Charles Lewis, Paris, Apr. 25, [1851]; Feb. 18, 1953, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 87 - 88)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Gye, Frederick, [Paris], [Apr. 17-18, 1953], (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 89)
      [From Maggs Brothers]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Hainl, Francois Georges, Avignon, Paris, 1845 - 1861, (7 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 90 - 96)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Halevy, Fromenthal, [Paris], Nov. 29, [1859]; Aug. 11, 1861, (2 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 97 - 98)
      [Original in Mina Curtiss Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Halle, Charles, [London], Paris, {Mar. - Apr. 1848]; Apr. 4, 1860, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 99 - 100)
      [Originals in British Museum]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Heinze, M., [Paris], Sep. 1866, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 101)
      [Original in Charles Munch Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Heller, n.p., n.d., (2 a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 102 - 103)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Herbeck, Johann, Paris, Dec. 12, 1864, (1p. a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Hopkins, Jerome, Paris, Dec. 6, 1863, (2 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 105 - 106)
      [Originals in Sylvia Wright Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: d'Indy, Madame la Comtesse Wilfried, Paris, Apr. 25. [1855], (a.l.s. (Typescript and ms. copy, ) (Box 3, Folder 107)
      [Original in Bibliotheque du Conservatoire]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: l'Intendant general, Paris, Dec. 17, 1834, (4p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Jahn, Otto, Paris, Jan. 7, 1854, (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Janin, Jules, [Paris], 1838 - 1840, (3 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 110 - 112)
      [Originals in: Stanford University Libraries; Harvard University Library; Sibley Musical Library, U. of Rochester]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Jullien, Marcel Bernard, Paris, Apr. 20, 1867, (a.l.s. (Typescript and ms. copy), ) (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Kistner, Julius, Paris, Dresden, Dec. 9, n.y.; Apr. 14, 1954, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 114 - 115)
      [Originals in: British Museum; R. F. Kallir Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Krebs, Carl, Hanover, Apr. 1, 1854, (1p. a.l.s. (Typescript and ms. copy), ) (Box 3, Folder 116)
      [Original in Edward H. Wannemacher Collection, Philadelphia]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Kreutzer, Leon, [Paris], [Feb. 24, 1850], (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Lebouc, M., n.p., n.d., (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 118)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Lecomte, M., n.p., n.d., (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 3, Folder 119)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Legouve, Ernest, [Paris], Aug. 18, 1864, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 120)
      [From: Revue Musicale, Aug. 15, 1903, 430.]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Leroy, Loius, [Paris], Feb. 14, 1858, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 121)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Leslie, H. D.], [Paris], May 7, [1848], (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 122)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Liszt, Franz, [Paris], 1836-1839, (3 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 123)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Litolff, Henry, Baden Baden, Aug. 16, n.y., (1p. a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 3, Folder 124)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Littleton, Henry], Paris, Sep. 6, 1858, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 3, Folder 125)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Lotto, Isidore, [Paris], Jun. 17, 1862, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: de la Madeleine, Stephen, [Paris], 1829 - 1862, (9 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 2 - 10)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Marmontel, A. F., [Paris], Mar. 28, 1963, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Mereaux, M., London, Oct., n.y., (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ministre de la Guerre, M., Paris, Oct. - Dec. 1837, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 13 - 14)
      [Originals in Bibliotheque de Grenoble; archives of Ministre de la Guerre]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ministre de l'Interieur, M., [Paris], Apr. 3, 1844, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ministre Secretaire d'Etat de l'Interieur, M., Paris, Aug. 20, 1828, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 4, Folder 16)
      [Originals in Cortot Collection. Includes reply.]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Molmer, St. Petersburg, Feb. 1, 1868, (4p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Montfort, Alexandre, Le Cote St. Andre, Jan. 10, 1831, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 18)
      [Original in Collection of Andre Mayer, Paris]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Morel, Auguste, [Paris], Mar. 9, 1860, (1p. a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Munzloff, M., n.p., n.d., (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Mutee, M., [Paris], Apr. 6, 1862, (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Novello, Alfred, London, Paris, 1855 - 1856, (6 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 22 - 27)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: l'Orpheon, directors of, [1860-1861], ( 1p. a.l.s. (Typescript and ms. copy), ) (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: [Nicolo Paganini], n.p., Dec. 18, 1838, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Perrin, Emile, Paris, Jan. 10, 1863, (4p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Pohl, Richard, [Paris], 1858-1863, (7 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 31 - 37)
      [Originals in Harvard University Library]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Prevost, Hyppolite, [Paris], Nov. 27, 1859, (1p. An.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Prussia, King of, [Paris], Mar. 24, 1843, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Raymond, n.p., n.d., (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Raymond, Xavier, [Paris], Aug. 21, 1851, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Reber, Henri, Paris, Nov. 27, [1838], (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Rety, Francois Hippolyte, Rome, London, Sep. 14, 1831; Jun. 29, 1848, (2 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 43 - 44)
      [Originals in R. F. Kallir Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ricordi, I., Paris, Apr. 17, 1853, (2p. a.l.s. (Photostat, pos. and neg.), ) (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ricou, M., [Paris], [Apr. 1834], (a.l.s. (Typescript & ms. copy), ) (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Ritter, Theodore, London, Paris, 1855 - 1861, (4 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 47 - 50)
      [Originals in: British Museum; Stanford University Libraries]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Rocquemont, M., [Paris], [Apr. 1, 1854], (1p. a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Royer, Alphonse, [Paris], Jul. 3, n.y.; May 31, 1861, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 52 - 53)
      [Originals in: Bibliotheque de Grenoble; Sibley Musical Library, U. of Rochester]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Sainton, Prosper, London, Paris, 1850 - 1856, (4 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 54 - 57)
      [Originals in Richard Capell Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Saphir, [Moritz Gottlieb], [Paris], Apr. 29, 1855, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 58)
      [Original in posession of Larry Simmons, Philadelphia]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Sax, Adolphe, [Paris], [1843], (a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 59)
      [Original in collection of Edwin F. Goldman]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Schlesinger, Maurice, [Paris], Mar. - Nov. 1838, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat, typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 60 - 61)
      [Originals in: Stanford University Libraries; Edwin Franko Goldman Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Schlosser, Friedrich, Paris, Jan. 28, 1844; Apr. 29 1853, (2 a.l.s. (Typescript), ) (Box 4, Folder 62 - 63)
      [Originals in: Collection of Arnold Whitridge; NYPL]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Schoelcher, Victor, [Paris], Feb. 1, 1839, (3p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 64)
      [Original in C. Hopkinson Collection]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Schonenberger, M., Paris, Jan. 3, 1860, (1p. a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Seghers, M., [Paris], Dec. 16, 1832; [Nov. 1861], (2 a.l.s. Typescript) (Box 4, Folder 66 - 67)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Silas, Edouard, Paris, Mar. 3, 1860; Jan. 6, 1864, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 68 - 69)
      [Originals in: C. Hopkinson Collection; British Museum]
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Spontini, Gasparo, [Paris], Mar. 29, 1832, (2p. a.l. (Typescipt), 1p a.l. (photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Spontini, Madame [Erard], [Paris], Sep. 5, [1854], (1p. a.l.s. (Typescript and ms copy), ) (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Berlioz, Hector to: Stassoff, Vladimir, Paris, Sep. 10, 1862, (1p. a.l.s. (Typescript, and ms. copy), ) (Box 4, Folder 72)
      [From: O. Fouque, Les revolutionnaires de la musique, 231]
    - Berlioz, Hector to [Steinway, Theodore], Plombieres; Paris, Aug. 28, 1856; Sep. 25, 1867, (2 a.l.s. (Photostat), ) (Box 4, Folder 73 - 74)
      [Original in Steinway family]